Paul Philips Cooke 100 100
Stage
Paul Philips Cooke Papers
1871-2000
Stage
100
16 cubic feet; 16 boxes
The Paul Philips Cooke Papers document Cooke's career in education and DC government, as well as his participation in the struggle for civil rights and desegregation of DC schools. The collection contains documents from Cooke's tenure at the DC Teachers' College and work with the University of the District of Columbia's College of Business and Public Management, scholarships and awards programs and other local organizations including the Board of Education of Kiryas Joel Village, NAACP, and Anthony Bowen YMCA.
Biographical / Historical
Paul Cooke was born in Harlem, NY on June 29, 1917 and grew up in Washington, DC. He graduated in 1933 from Dunbar High School, where he was the first baseman on the varsity baseball team. He graduated from Miner Teachers College in 1937. He received two master's degrees, one in education from New York University and another in English language and literature from the Catholic University of America.
Cooke received a doctorate in education from Columbia University in 1947. He joined Miner's faculty in the mid-1940s, and worked as a proponent for the desegregation of public schools. In 1955, DC Miner Teachers College and Wilson Teachers College merged to become DC Teachers College, an integrated institution. Cooke became president of the college in 1966 and retired in 1974 before it was absorbed into the University of the District of Columbia. During his eight-year tenure at DC Teachers College, enrollment tripled and the school began taking on an expanded role in the community by sponsoring street patrols to ensure residents' safety and operating a youth recreation program. Cooke served as president of local teachers' organizations including Local 27 of the American Federation of Teachers and also worked to improve learning conditions at Cardozo and Dunbar High Schools.
After retiring in 1974, Dr. Cooke wrote and spoke widely about the history of Washington. He was the director of international programs for the American Association of State Colleges and Universities and served as a consultant to Howard University, the University of the District of Columbia, the Smithsonian Anacostia Community Museum and the World Peace Through Law Center, a Washington-based nonprofit organization that did work globally with United States Agency for International Development (USAID) grants.
Scope and Contents
The Paul Philips Cooke Papers document Cooke's career in education and DC government, as well as his participation in the struggle for civil rights and desegregation of DC schools. The collection contains documents from Cooke's tenure at the DC Teachers' College and work with the University of the District of Columbia's College of Business and Public Management, scholarships and awards programs and other local organizations including the Board of Education of Kiryas Joel Village, NAACP, and Anthony Bowen YMCA. Also included are academic history symposium files, audiotapes from the New York Times Book Review and Washingtonian Magazine, court papers, copies of The Torch and Cosmos Club, and research files (clippings, tapes, programs) on the Black Power Movement.
Custodial History
Gift of Paul Philips Cooke, 1998-2005.
African Americans
- Series 1
  - Advisory Neighborhood Councils, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Advisory Neighborhood Council Commission ANC's (1 of 3), 1974-1975 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Advisory Neighborhood Council Commission ANC's (2 of 3), 1974-1975 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Advisory Neighborhood Council Commission ANC's (3 of 3), 1974-1975 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Civilian Compliant Review Board, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - D.C Revitalization, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Federal Civil Rights Enforcement Budget Report Correspondence, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Mrs. Roxana Deane envelope, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Forum on Police - Community Relations in D.C., 1980 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Catalog of Publication US Commission on Civil Rights September, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - State Advisory Committee Members Memo, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - News Release - Edward Rutledge Appointment, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - U.S Commission of Civil Rights, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - State Advisory Committee, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - U.S Commission on Civil Rights State Advisory Committee Chairperson Annual Meeting, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Revised Administrative Instructions, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence - Request for Views of the Commission on S. 1722 and H.R 6915, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Congressional Record, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Statement by the President Press Release, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Testimony by the Staff Director Before the Commission on Security and Cooperation in Europe, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - 1981 Civil Rights Budget: An Analysis, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Policy Guidelines/Minutes/Status Report, 1979-1984 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Debutant Cotillion 1992 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Benjamin H. Alexander - Ph.D President University of D.C., 1982 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Contribution of D.C Documents Relating to Post Secondary Education in DC to the University of DC, 1975-1976 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Central Cardozo File 1948-1950 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Interracial Workshop, 1947-1954 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Annual Report of President of Miner Teachers College, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Education: The Disadvantaged Model School Division, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Miner Teachers College Class of 1937 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Talks of A College Professor and President Addresses/Eulogies/Lectures/Remarks/Speeches, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Addresses/Lectures/other talks - A College President/College Professor/School Teacher, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Talks 1935-1988 Addresses/Lectures/Remarks/Speeches, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Addresses/Lectures/other Talks, 1933-1993 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Addresses/Lectures/other Talks, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Publications, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Talks of a College Professor and President 1933-1988, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - PSDC 1955 Anecdotal Reports and Records School Integration in Washington the First Year 1954-1955, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Journal of Negro History/UNE Articles and Reviews [Journal of Negro Education], 1949-1982 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - The Normal Schools: District of Columbia Paul Phillips Cooke, 1986 1986 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Public Higher Education in DC, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Address Lectures/other talks, 1933-1993 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Address Lectures/other Talks, 1933-1993 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - The Centennial Drama Miner Teachers College, 1951 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Consumers Council on Human Relations, 1961 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Southwestern Citizenship and Protection Program, 1959 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Miners Teacher College Plays/Cantana/Opera - 1946-1955, 1995 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Publications and other writing, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Mary Church Terrell: A Tribute, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Mary Church Terrell, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Graduates of DC Teachers College 1972-1971, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Perspectives on Preparation of American Teachers and Educational Leaders, 1990 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Improving the Retention of unprepared college student, 1987-03 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Talks/Addresses/Lectures/Remarks/Descriptive Bibliography/Speeches, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Addresses/Lectures/other talks, 1933-1993 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - St. Martin Correspondence, undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Cosmos Club, 1995-1996 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Mass Ave Research, undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Girard Block Association, 1981 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Historical Survey of Columbia, 1982 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Cosmos Club Washington D.C, 2000-01-01 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Cosmo Club Washington D.C., 09-01-1985 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Constitution Decisions, 1993 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Recorder of Deeds, 1871 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Clips 1949-1963 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Congress 1871 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Civil Rights, 1873 1873 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Redevelopment, 1964-1995 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Llewllyn J. Scott… Humanitarian and the life of Benjamin Banneker, undated (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Act Regulating the sale 9m Restraints, 1873 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - DC Civil Rights Law 1873 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - The Columbia Historical Society Financial Statements and Author's Report, 1982 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Terrell Law, 1944-1946 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Cosmos History, 1962 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Constitutional and Territorial Government of DC Democracy - Federalism and Establishment, 1987 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Cosmos Pamphlets, undated (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Legislative Assembly of DC Act, 1873 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - 41st Congress Legislation and Negro Education, 1871 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - New Negro Alliance Year Book, 1939 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - The City on the Hill: Race Relations in Washington D.C - 1865-1885, 1975 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Cosmos for the Arts, 1995 (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - Civil Rights DC 1872 (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - Cosmos Member, 1982-1984 (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - Cosmos Forum Luncheon, 1977-1978 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Cosmos Club, 1982-1993 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Elect Evening Star, 1871-06-20 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Graduates of DC Teachers College and Predecessor Institutions 1873-1977, undated (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Plays for Children 1948-1955, undated (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Mary Elizabeth Cooke Bukner- Photograph at the White House, undated (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Family Souvenirs of Freedom, 1976 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - The Cookes - Biographical Dictionary and Lectures, undated (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Bergman News Articles, 1946 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Emancipation 1862, undated (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Appreciation Correspondence, 1995 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Miner Students, 1999 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Bergman Correspondence, 1946 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - DC Teachers College Photographs and Essays 1966-1974, undated (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Photo Essay of Paul Phillips Cooke 1917-2004, undated (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Audio Recordings, undated (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Clips DC 77-78, 1978-1978 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Black Power Clips, 1964-1968 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - DCTC Tapes of Trojan Interview, undated (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Twenty-Second Annual Scholarship and Awards Banquet, 1993 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - DC Humanities Council, 1995 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - DC Financial Responsibility and Management Assistance Authority Strategic Plan, undated (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Graduates of DC Teachers College and Processor Institutions, 1874-1977 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - John Carroll Board of Gov., 1971-1975 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - John Carrol Com. Social and Civic, 1972 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Leadership Conference on Civil Rights, 1981-1999 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Leadership Conference on Civil Rights, 1995 1995 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Reslyn W. Henley, 1997 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Theodore Percy Jenifer Funeral Program, 1998 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Junior Citizen Corps, 1978 (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Gasch, 1979-2000 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Joyce A Ladner - Sociology Reflection on Teacher Education, 1997 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Howard University Correspondence, 1995 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Award Dinner - Washington Equal Justice Award Dinner Program, 1991 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - 1978-1979 Annual Report NAACP Legal Defense Fund, 1980 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - 50th Anniversary A Victories of Principal Celebration, 1990 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Leadership Conference on Civil Rights Hubert H. Humphrey Civil Rights Award, 1996 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Crime in the Nation's Capital Annual Report, 1947-1954 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Public Laws and Bills, 1965-1970 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Public Law 85-838, 1958 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - DC Teachers College Catalog, 1968-1970 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - New Negro Alliance Year Book, 1939 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Klan Segment #1, 1976 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Graduates of DC Teachers College, 1972-1977 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Cooke: Mary Church Terrell, 1978 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - The Washington Torch Club Correspondence, 1993 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - The Torch Spring/Summer 1992 Vol. 64. no. 3 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - The Torch Winter 1992 Vo. 64 No. 2 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - The Torch Winter 1993 Vol. 65 No. 2 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Torch, 1991-1993 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Memorial Celebration Russell Henri Viau, 1999 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - DC Teachers College Catalog 1971/1972 (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Continental 35th Anniversary Society Inc., 1988 (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - The Torch, 1994-1998 (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - The Torch, 1994-1998 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - The Story of Torch: The First 50 years of International Association of Torch Clubs, 1991 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Washington City Breakfast Group, 1993 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Old Ebbitt Grill Menu, undated (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Board of Ed Kiryas Joel Village School District v Louis Grumet, 1994 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Catering Info, undated (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - MLK Plays, 1954-1956 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Official Records of DC: Present Status and Opportunities for Improvement, 1983 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - John Carroll Society Membership Directory, 1998-2000 (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - History of the City of Washington, 1914 (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - A History of the National Capital, 1914 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Wash Past and Present excerpt by Proctor, 1930 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - A Shepherd, 1992 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - CHS Records, 1950-1952 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Mickerson Testimony, undated (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Clippings, 1968 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Acts of Congress, 1790-1883 (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - D.C 1796-1871 Talk Before Wash City Breakfast Group, 1985 (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Clippings, 1961-1968 (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - St. Martin de Porres Hospice - L.J Scott, undated (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - Cosmos Club Travel Group, 2000 (Box 14, Folder 11)
  - Taxation and Philosophy - Washington Torch Club Fall 1984, 1984-1985 (Box 14, Folder 12)
  - Programs, 1998-1999 (Box 14, Folder 13)
  - Cooke Cosmos Club, 1978 (Box 14, Folder 14)
  - Cosmos Club Rules, 1962 (Box 14, Folder 15)
  - Cosmos 1978 Events (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Cosmo Club Members, 1978-1996 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - John Carroll, 1974 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - John Carroll Society, 1971-1978 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Educating America: Black Universities and Colleges - Strengths and Crises, 1990 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Michael B. Basch, 1996-1999 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Midtown Youth Academy, 1984-1985 (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Monday Morning Breakfast Club, 1996 (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - The Cosmo Club Papers, 2001 (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - Women/Cosmos Club, 1980-2000 (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - Gandalf, 1987 (Box 15, Folder 11)
  - Nomination for Membership in Cosmos of Benjamin H. Alexander, 1983 (Box 15, Folder 12)
  - Symposium of the History of the D.C Office of the Secretary, 1985 (Box 15, Folder 13)
  - Dunbar Newspaper Articles, 1999 (Box 15, Folder 14)
  - Cooke 1993 Kappa Alpha Pamphlet (Box 15, Folder 15)
  - 1994 ASAHL Papers (Box 15, Folder 16)
  - A Voice from the South, 1980 (Box 15, Folder 17)
  - Thurgood Marshall Center Correspondence, 1996 (Box 15, Folder 18)
  - Black History Article and Buck Covington and the YMCA, 1996-2000 (Box 15, Folder 19)
  - Steven Correspondence, undated (Box 15, Folder 20)
  - New York Times Book Review Tapes, 2000 (Box 16, Folder 1)